Antonio Sotomayor
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Antonio Sotomayor papers
circa 1920-1988
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Sotomayor, Antonio
1.7 linear feet
The collection documents the career of painter and illustrator, Antonio Sotomayor, his interest in Latin American art and artists, and his association with the San Francisco arts community. Materials found in the collection include letters, writings, sketches and sketchbooks, printed material and photographs.
Biographical Note
Antonio Sotomayor was born in Bolvia and came to San Francisco in 1923. He was educated at the Escuela de Belleas Arts in La Paz and the Hopkins Institute of Art in San Francisco. Primarily known for his murals and paintings, Sotomayor was also an illustrator, caricaturist, designer, ceramicist, and educator. Over the course of his career his work was exhibited in the United States, France, Italy, Spain, Mexico, and South America and he became known as the popular "artist laureate" of San Francisco where he lived with his wife, Grace. He died of cancer in 1985 at the age of 82.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists primarily of correspondence, writings, artwork, printed material, and photographs documenting Sotomayor's career, his interest in Latin American art and artists, and his association with the San Francisco arts community.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as six series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1931-1988, undated (box 1, 21 folders)
Series 2: Writings, 1932-1946, undated (box 1, 11 folders)
Series 3: Artwork, 1935, undated (box 1, 23 folders)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1935-1987 (boxes 1-2, 12 folders)
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1920-1984, undated (box 2, 13 folders)
Series 6: Oversized Material, 1941, 1958, undated (2 OV folders)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms.
Subjects:
Farr, Fred, 1914-1973; Fried, Alexander, 1902-1988; Gerstle, William Lewis, b. 1868; Labaudt, Lucien, 1880-1943; Little, Philip, 1857-1942; Moya del Pino, J.; Oldfield, Otis, 1890-1969; Pflueger, Timothy Ludwig, 1892-1946; Rivera, Diego, 1886-1957; Salinger, Pierre
Subjects-Topical:
Mural painting and decoration -- 20th century; Illustration; Caricatures and cartoons; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- California -- San Francisco; Hispanic American artists; Cartoonists -- California -- San Francisco; Illustrators -- California -- San Francisco; Muralists -- California -- San Francisco; Painters -- California -- San Francisco
Types of Materials:
Sketchbooks; Photographs; Works of art; Sketches
Names:
Entenza, John, 1903-; Franco, Johan, 1908-; Morley, Grace, 1900-; Moya del Pino, J.; Long, Emilie; Orozco, José Clemente, 1883-1949; Reed, Alma M.; Robinson, Elmer E. (Elmer Edwin), b. 1894; Salinger, Jehanne Bietry; Sauer, Carl Ortwin, 1889-; Sotomayor, Grace; Von Hagen, Victor Wolfgang, 1908-; Pan American Union; Delphic Studios
Provenance
The Antonio Sotomayor papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by Grace Sotomayor in 1998.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on microfilm reels 4792-4793. The microfilm is available for interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Correspondence and Biographical Material, 1931-1988, undated, Series 1:; (box 1, 21 folders)
  This series contains correspondence relating to Sotomayor's mural commissions, paintings and caricatures, illustrations for various publications, exhibitions at museums and galleries, and lectures. Correspondents include John Entenza, Johan Franco, Emilie Long, Grace L. McCann Morely of the San Francisco Museum of Art, José Moya del Pino, José Clemente Orozco, the Pan American Union, Alma Reed of the Delphic Studios, San Francisco mayor Elmer Robinson, Carl Sauer, Grace Sotomayor, and ethnologist Wolfgang von Hagen. There is also a folder of biographical material containing lists of some of Sotomayor's work and exhibitions from the 1920s to circa 1963.
  - Correspondence, 1931-1973, 1988, undated, (9 folders) (Box 1, Reel 4792)
  - Correspondence Re: Exhibitions and Lectures, 1938-1947, (5 folders) (Box 1, Reel 4792)
  - Correspondence Re: Book Illustrations, Magazines and Newspapers, 1938-1948, (6 folders) (Box 1, Reel 4792)
  - Biographical Material, circa 1963 (Box 1, Reel 4792)
- Writings, 1932-1946, undated, Series 2:; (box 1, 11 folders)
  This series contains two notebooks of biographical notes on Latin American artists, manuscripts and copies of manuscripts on Hispanic American artists and caricature, and articles and lectures by Sotomayor. There are also writings by others on Sotomayor, and the transcript of an interview of Sotomayor conducted by Grace Moreley regarding Latin American Art.
  - Writings by Sotomayor (Box 1, Reel 4792)
    - Notebooks (in Spanish), undated, (1 folder, 2 notebooks) (Box 1, Reel 4792)
    - "Hispanic American Art," undated (Box 1, Reel 4792)
    - Lecture to the Sigma Delta Pi, undated (Box 1, Reel 4792)
    - "Caricature and American Caricaturists," 1941 (Box 1, Reel 4792)
    - Newspaper Articles, 1932-1933, undated (Box 1, Reel 4792)
    - Radio Interview Transcript (in Spanish and English), circa 1939 (Box 1, Reel 4792)
  - Writings by Others (Box 1, Reel 4792)
    - "Sotomayor" by Joe Danysh, undated (Box 1, Reel 4792)
    - Press Release by Edward Perkins, undated (Box 1, Reel 4792)
    - "Bolivia Speaks in the Art of Antonio Sotomayor," by Jehane Biétry Salinger, undated (Box 1, Reel 4792)
    - "Antonio Sotomayor" for Bulletin of the Pan American Union, by Jehane Biétry Salinger, 1933 (Box 1, Reel 4792)
    - "Sotomayor, Pintor de Bolivia" for Bulletin of the Pan American Union, by José Goméz Sicre, 1946 (Box 1, Reel 4792)
- Artwork, 1935, undated, Series 3:; (box 1, 23 folders)
  This series contains 130 sketches and 35 sketchbooks, mostly containing travel sketches done in South America, the Middle East, and Europe, particularly Italy. One volume contains caricatures of prominent architects. Sotomayor's mock up for the unpublished Where San Francisco Dines by Collier Connell can also be found here. See also Series 6: Oversized Material.
  - Loose Sketches, undated (Box 1, Reel 4792)
  - Loose Travel Sketches, Europe, undated (Box 1, Reel 4792)
  - Sketchbook of Travel Sketches, Europe, undated, (1 folder, 2 sketchbooks) (Box 1, Reel 4792)
  - Sketchbook of Travel Sketches, Italy, undated, (4 folders, 7 sketchbooks) (Box 1, Reel 4792)
  - Sketchbook of Travel Sketches, Middle East, undated (Box 1, Reel 4792)
  - Sketchbook of Travel Sketches, South America, undated, (5 folders, 8 sketchbooks) (Box 1, Reel 4792)
  - Sketchbook of Travel Sketches, California, undated, (1 folder, 2 sketchbooks) (Box 1, Reel 4792)
  - Sketchbook, "AIA Building Production Exhibition," undated (Box 1, Reel 4792)
  - Sketchbooks, Miscellaneous, undated, (5 folders, 11 sketchbooks) (Box 1, Reel 4793)
  - Book of Ink Drawings/Illustrations, undated (Box 1, Reel 4793)
  - Mock Up of Illustrations for Book Where San Francisco Dines by Collier Connell, 1935 (Box 1, Reel 4793)
  - Artwork by Others, undated (Box 1, Reel 4793)
- Printed Material, 1935-1987, Series 4:; (boxes 1-2, 12 folders)
  This series contains clippings, exhibition catalogs and announcements, and several publications containing illustrations by Sotomayor.
  - Clippings, circa 1942-1987, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 4793)
  - Exhibition Catalog, San Francisco Museum of Art, 1935 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
  - Exhibition Catalog, M.H. de Young Memorial Museum, 1943 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Cincinnati Art Museum, 1945 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1946-1978, undated (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
  - Publication Illustrations (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
    - The Coast, Sept., Oct., 1938 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
    - The Coast, Feb., Oct., Dec., 1939 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
    - Modern Music, 1945 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
    - La Revue Moderne, 1955 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
  - Publications, The Coast and Saturday Review, 1939, 1953 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
  - Publications, The Kerlan Collection, Walter Library, University of Minnestota, 1971 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
- Photographs, circa 1920-1984, undated, Series 5:; (box 2, 13 folders)
  Photographs found here include portraits of Sotomayor, and photographs of the artist with family and friends, including Grace Sotomayor, Fred Farr, Al Fried, William Gerstle, Lucien Labaudt, Philip Little, José Moya Del Pino, Otis Odfield, Timothy Pflueger, Diego Rivera, Pierre Salinger. There are also photographs of Sotomayor with members of the Pan American Union and the Bohemian Club, and of artwork, including some in the Sotomayor residence. See also Series 6: Oversized Material.
  - Portraits of Sotomayor, 1924-1984, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
  - Family and Friends, circa 1920-1983, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
  - Scrapbook of Family and Friends (loose pages), circa 1947 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
  - Group Photographs, 1974-1983, undated (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1952-1983, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
  - Photographs of Artwork in Sotomoyor Residence, circa 1952 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
  - Photograph of Bathroom Rug by Grace Sotomayor, undated (Box 2 (hol), Reel 4793)
- Oversized Material, 1941, 1958, undated, Series 6:; (2 OV folders)
  This series contains sketches, an exhibition poster, and several oversized photographs of artwork by Sotomayor and of Sotomayor with friends (duplicate of photograph in Series 5: Photographs).
  - Ink Drawing, "Peace is Sharing," undated (Box 3 (ov), Reel 4792)
  - Sketch of Union Square Office Mural and Related Letter, 1958 (Box 3 (ov), Reel 4792)
  - Exhibition Poster for Illinois Art Gallery, undated (Box 4 (ov), Reel 4793)
  - Oversized Photographs, 1941, undated (Box 4 (ov), Reel 4793)